
   <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
     <channel>
       <title>coronavirus on Aditya Bose</title>
       <link>https://adbose.github.io/tags/coronavirus/</link>
       <description>Recent content in coronavirus on Aditya Bose</description>
       <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
       <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2020 - Aditya Bose</copyright>
       <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 02:29:14 +0530</lastBuildDate>
       
           <atom:link href="https://adbose.github.io/tags/coronavirus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
       
       
       <item>
         <title>Quarantine</title>
         <link>https://adbose.github.io/posts/01/</link>
         <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 02:29:14 +0530</pubDate>
         
         <guid>https://adbose.github.io/posts/01/</guid>
         <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been 100 days of Coronavirus today&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the last day of 2019, China announced it had detected a “pneumonia of unknown cause” in the city of Wuhan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the first time the world got a notice of what was about to hit.
One hundred days later, the Covid-19 virus has spread to almost every country and has resulted in billions of people now living under lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is an infectious disease caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). Since the first mention of it appearing in Wuhan, it has spread now all over the globe, resulting in the ongoing 2019–20 coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, over a million people have been infected, close to a hundred thousand people have lost their lives, and the disease is still spreading exponentially.
Schools, universities, workplaces and bubsinesses are shut down, people are losing their jobs, and the whole world is slowly falling into to an economic recession.
But in order to flatten the curve of the spread of the disease, it is our best option to fight the disease in the absense of a cure or a vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I too have quarantined myself at home during this lockdown, trying to responsibly play my part in the collective effort of containing the spread of the disease, while also staying positive and productive in my daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often throughout the day, I find myself checking on twitter, or the many online forums and sites like &lt;a href=&#34;covid19india.org&#34;&gt;India Covid-19 Tracker&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;worldometers.info/coronavirus/&#34;&gt;Worldometer&lt;/a&gt; Coronavirus tracker, &lt;a href=&#34;covidvisualizer.com&#34;&gt;CovidVisualizer&lt;/a&gt;, to get the latest news and developments on the Covid19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
       </item>
       
     </channel>
   </rss>
